<div3 id="elem.6.19" n="19" type="number" org="uniform" sample="complete">
      <head>PROPOSITION 19.</head>
      <p><emph>Similar triangles are to one another in the duplicate ratio of the corresponding sides</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>DEF</emph> be similar triangles having the angle at <emph>B</emph> equal to the angle at <emph>E</emph>, and such that, as <emph>AB</emph> is to <emph>BC</emph>, so <lb n="5"/>is <emph>DE</emph> to <emph>EF</emph>, so that <emph>BC</emph> corresponds to <emph>EF</emph>; [<ref target="elem.5.def.11" targOrder="U">V. Def. 11</ref>] I say that the triangle <emph>ABC</emph> has to the triangle <emph>DEF</emph> a ratio duplicate of that which <emph>BC</emph> has to <emph>EF</emph>. <figure/>
      </p>
      <p>For let a third proportional <emph>BG</emph> be taken to <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>EF</emph>, so that, as <emph>BC</emph> is to <emph>EF</emph>, so is <emph>EF</emph> to <emph>BG</emph>; [<ref target="elem.6.11" targOrder="U">VI. 11</ref>] <lb n="10"/>and let <emph>AG</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Since then, as <emph>AB</emph> is to <emph>BC</emph>, so is <emph>DE</emph> to <emph>EF</emph>, therefore, alternately, as <emph>AB</emph> is to <emph>DE</emph>, so is <emph>BC</emph> to <emph>EF</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.16" targOrder="U">V. 16</ref>] <pb n="233"/></p>
      <p>But, as <emph>BC</emph> is to <emph>EF</emph>, so is <emph>EF</emph> to <emph>BG</emph>; therefore also, as <emph>AB</emph> is to <emph>DE</emph>, so is <emph>EF</emph> to <emph>BG</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.11" targOrder="U">V. 11</ref>] <lb n="15"/></p>
      <p>Therefore in the triangles <emph>ABG</emph>, <emph>DEF</emph> the sides about the equal angles are reciprocally proportional. </p>
      <p>But those triangles which have one angle equal to one angle, and in which the sides about the equal angles are reciprocally proportional, are equal; [<ref target="elem.6.15" targOrder="U">VI. 15</ref>] <lb n="20"/>therefore the triangle <emph>ABG</emph> is equal to the triangle <emph>DEF</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now since, as <emph>BC</emph> is to <emph>EF</emph>, so is <emph>EF</emph> to <emph>BG</emph>, and, if three straight lines be proportional, the first has to the third a ratio duplicate of that which it has to the second, [<ref target="elem.5.def.9" targOrder="U">V. Def. 9</ref>] therefore <emph>BC</emph> has to <emph>BG</emph> a ratio duplicate of that which <emph>CB</emph>
       <lb n="25"/>has to <emph>EF</emph>. </p>
      <p>But, as <emph>CB</emph> is to <emph>BG</emph>, so is the triangle <emph>ABC</emph> to the triangle <emph>ABG</emph>; [<ref target="elem.6.1" targOrder="U">VI. 1</ref>] therefore the triangle <emph>ABC</emph> also has to the triangle <emph>ABG</emph> a ratio duplicate of that which <emph>BC</emph> has to <emph>EF</emph>. <lb n="30"/></p>
      <p>But the triangle <emph>ABG</emph> is equal to the triangle <emph>DEF</emph>; therefore the triangle <emph>ABC</emph> also has to the triangle <emph>DEF</emph> a ratio duplicate of that which <emph>BC</emph> has to <emph>EF</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. </p>
      <div4 id="elem.6.19.p.1" type="porism" org="uniform" sample="complete">
       <head>PORISM.</head>
       <p>From this it is manifest that, if three straight <lb n="35"/>lines be proportional, then, as the first is to the third, so is the figure described on the first to that which is similar and similarly described on the second. Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
      <note n="4" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p><hi rend="bold">and such that, as AB is to BC, so is DE to EF</hi>, literally <quote>(triangles) having the angle at <emph>B</emph> equal to the angle at <emph>E</emph>, and (<emph>having</emph>), <emph>as AB to BC</emph>, <emph>so DE to EF</emph>.</quote>
</p>
      </note>
     </div3>
     
